In the
time
of the
warring
states
A time of corruption
There existed
an
ultimate
Way of
the Sword
that used
no swords
Oushuu
Hida Castle
反逆者　飛騨鷹比等
The rebel,
Hida Takahito.
Kyotouryuu's...
虚刀流の
I see.
そうか 僕はこういうふうに失敗するのか
So this is how I'll meet my end.
今となってはせんなきことだ
At this point, it is unavoidable.
Miss?
お客さん あっ 見えてきましたよ
It's in sight now.
What kind of business might you have on an uninhabited island like that?
あんな無人島に何のご用なんですかね？
It's not an uninhabited island.
無人島などではない
あれは　大乱の英雄の流刑の地
That's the island where the hero of the rebellion was exiled to.
Zettou
Kanna
The one who came to power after the rebellion, Shogun Yanari, fearing the power of the hero of the rebellion, Yasuri Mutsue,
大乱後の世を治めた将軍家鳴は
英雄鑢六枝の剣法を恐れ
彼の家族と共にこの無人島に幽閉しました
exiled him along with his family to this uninhabited island.
それから２０年
For 20 years, no one else has stepped foot on the island.
誰もこの地を訪れることはありませんでした
あー面倒だな
What a hassle.
何しているの　七花
What are you doing, Shichika?
Nee-chan...
姉ちゃん
ああ　かめの水がなくなりそうだったから
It looks like the cistern's out of water, so...
そんな格好で出てくるなよ 寒いだろう
Don't come out dressed like that, it's cold.
I'm fine.
大丈夫
It feels good if it's just for a bit.
少しくらいなら気持ちいいぐらいよ
Also, wasn't it my turn to do the housework today?
それより　今日の家事当番はわたしだったはずだけど
Was it?
そうだっけ？
私のことを腫れ物みたいに扱うのはやめてって言ってるでしょ
Didn't I tell you to stop treating me so delicately?
I wasn't trying to.
そんなつもりはないよ
It's fine.
いいだろ これも修行の一環だ
This is just another part of my training.
余計な気回しを教えた覚えはなくってよ
I don't remember teaching you to be overly considerate.
See, I told you to go back inside!
ほら うちに入ってろって
修行なんてもう何の意味もないじゃない
There's no reason for you to train anymore.
姉ちゃん
Nee-chan...
あなたの代で終わる流派を保つことに
What's the point in maintaining a combat style that will end with your generation?
どんな意味があるというの
I don't think I have a reason or anything.
意味なんて　考えてないけど
Hey, Shichika...
七花 父さんが死んでもう１年になるのよ
It's already been a year since father died.
そろそろいいんじゃないの
Can't you let it go already?
You don't need to say it like that...
そんな言い方はないだろ
昨日なんかさ新しい必殺技とか考えたんだぜ
I mean, just yesterday, I thought up a new ultimate move.
すげえカッコイイやつ…
It's a really awesome... move...
もともと　島流しの憂き目に遭ったのは父さん一人なんだし
To begin with, the one who got banished was father alone.
わたしは無理だけどあなた一人なら　舟を作って…
It'd be impossible for me, but you could make a boat for yourself and—
Don't be stupid!
バカなこと言わないでくれよ
This wasn't the kind of topic to bring up so early in the morning, was it.
起き抜けにする話じゃなかったわね
朝ご飯の支度はしておくから早く行ってらっしゃい
I'll prepare breakfast, so come back quickly.
Yeah.
新しい必殺技というのは
A new ultimate move, you say...
そうね 後で見てあげるわ
Show it to me later.
島を出るか そりゃいつかは出る話だと思ってたけどさ
Leave the island, huh?
I was expecting this topic to come up eventually,
これが唯一親父から受け継いだものだから
but this is the only thing I inherited from father, so...
大事にできるうちは大事にしておきたいんだ
I want to cherish it while I still can.
俺にはほかに何もないから
I don't have anything else, after all.
ハァ 面倒だなぁ
What a hassle.
親父がいたら　一発で切り捨て御免なんだろうが
If father was around he'd cut them down with one strike, too...
おい
Hey!
本土の人間か
A person from the mainland?
初めて見た
First time seeing one.
刀か
A sword?
それも初めて見た
First time seeing that too.
別によそ者だろうが誰だろうが入ってくるのは構わないんだけどよ
I don't personally mind if strangers or outsiders come here, but...
えっと
Um...
It's absolutely forbidden to carry blades onto this island.
この島への刃物の持ち込みは固く禁じられている
そうか
Is that so?
Yeah.
そうだ
それは失礼した
Pardon me, then.
知らなかったものでな 許しておけ
I wasn't aware.
Forgive me.
まあ　俺が決めたわけじゃないけどさ
Well, I wasn't the one who decided it.
あんたどうやってこの島に来た？
How did you come to this island?
By boat, of course.
舟で来たに決まっておる
特に俺が知りたいわけじゃないんだけどな
It's not like I particularly wanted to know,
こういうときはそうしろって言われてきたからな
but I'm supposed to ask that in this situation.
次は
Next is...
"What did you come here for?" right?
「何をしに来た？」だろ
そうだ 　何をしに来た
Yeah!
What did you come here for?
この島に虚刀流六代目 鑢六枝殿がおると聞いたのだが
I heard that the 6th generation Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Mutsue lives here.
Do you know him?
そなた　知らぬか？
親父なら死んだよ １年前
If you're talking about dad, he died.
A year ago.
そうか
I see...
今は　俺が当主だ
Right now I'm the family head.
The 7th generation Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Shichika.
虚刀流　七代目当主　鑢七花
ああいや これは愚問であった
I see.
Excuse my insensitivity.
２０年も前の話になる故な
My information was 20 years old, so I had considered he may have passed away.
そういうことも　あるとは思っておったが
I see...
なるほど いい体をしておる
He's got a strong body.
見てくれもまあまあだ
Doesn't look terrible either.
及第点といったところだな
I'd say it gets a passing grade.
何の話だ？
What are you talking about?
Ah, just talking to myself.
こっちの話だ
親父に用事だったみたいだけど悪かったな
It seems you had business with dad... sorry about that.
そのとおりだが　少し違う
You're right, but a little off.
用があったのは虚刀流当主にだ
My business is with the Kyotouryuu head.
故に六枝殿への用事は
Which means the business I had with Mutsue-dono has now changed to business with you.
今 そなたへの用事へと変わったのだ
七花 名乗りが遅れてしまったな わたしはとがめという
Shichika, I haven't told you my own name yet.
I am Togame.
Togame?
とがめ？変な名前
Weird name.
幕府の軍所総監督奇策士をなりわいとしておる
In my position as general director for the army of the Shogunate, I serve as a strategist.
まずは虚刀流試させてもらう
First of all, I'll be putting your Kyotouryuu to the test.
富岳三十六刀工が一人壬生傘麿呂が初期作品だ
This is an early work of Mibu Kasamaro, one of the 36 Fugaku swordsmiths.
Test?
試す？
That's what I said.
言葉どおりの意味だ 　参る！
Here I come!
ギャフン！？
鑢七花  奇策士とがめ
Yasuri Shichika and Togame the strategian.
The unfortunate meeting that began their destiny together,
数奇な運命を共にする２人が出会ったのは
まだ「ギャフン」という言葉が古くなかった時代
took place in the middle of January, in a time when the word "gyafun" was not yet outdated.
睦月中旬のことでした
I'm back.
ただいま
You said you're Togame the strategian, right?
奇策士のとがめさんでしたっけ？
この島にいらした初めてのお客さまですので
As you're our first visitor to this island, I'm not entirely sure how to welcome you...
もてなす作法を心得てはいませんが
いや こちらこそ突然の来訪 申し訳ない
No.
Pardon me for arriving here unannounced.
鑢六枝の娘七実と申します
I am Yasuri Mutsue's daughter, Nanami.
父を訪ねてこられたということですが
I heard you came to visit my father, but what connection do you have with him?
父とはどういった　ゆかりがおありなんですか？
I don't really have any "connection" to him.
ゆかりと言えるほどのつながりはない
ありませぬか
You don't?
ない ただの　飛び込みと考えてもらって結構だ 七実
No.
You can think of me as someone who just got involved, Nanami.
刀は預からせてもらっています
I'll keep your sword in my care.
この島は　刃物の持ち込み　使用を禁じていますから
It's forbidden to bring or use blades on this island.
虚刀流故にかな
Because of Kyotouryuu?
It's written as "the flow of the empty sword",
「虚しい刀の流れ」と書いて虚刀流
刀を用いない　闇の流派
a hidden style that uses no sword.
その技術がわずかに日の目を見たのは
The only ones who have openly demonstrated that style,
初代鑢一根と六代目当主鑢六枝の代だけ
were the first generation head Yasuri Kazuni...
and the 6th generation head Yasuri Mutsue.
When the whole country was plunged into rebellion, it was used in the midst of the chaotic battlefields; the deadliest of sword styles.
戦国と大乱
戦場の混乱との中でのみ振るわれる
最強の殺人剣術
あの男が七代目
That man is the 7th head.
Togame-san.
とがめさん あなたは弟に斬りつけようとしたとか？
You tried to attack my brother?
虚刀流の神髄を手っ取り早く見せてもらおうと思ってな
I really wanted to see Kyotouryuu in action.
I'm not used to that sort of stuff though.
しかし　慣れぬことはせんものだ
わたしは奇策士であって剣士ではない
I'm a strategian, not a swordsman.
That was still pretty impressive, given that.
そのわりには見事なものだったけどな
フッ あれだけは練習してきたのだ
I practiced that.
Why don't you keep practicing till you master it?
もっと最後まで練習してこい
That was a rather violent method, no?
乱暴な方法ですね
It's understandable if you see it that way, but I had my reasons.
そう思われても仕方ないが
こちらにも　思惑があった
鑢六枝の名は聞こえてはいたが
I'd heard of the name Yasuri Mutsue, but I don't know his face.
わたしはその顔を知らなかったからな
人違いが起きては大変だ
It would be big problem if I got the wrong person.
虚刀流の技を示してもらえるようならば
If he demonstrated Kyotouryuu, that would be more convincing than any name could be.
それが　何よりの名札代わりだ
Even if Mutsue were Shichika, it'd be the same?
六枝が七花でもそれは同じですか
では　もう一度試してみますか？
In that case, why don't you test him again?
小岩に足を取られたことは幸運だったと思ってください
Consider yourself lucky to have tripped over that rock.
If your blade had reached Shichika's body, you wouldn't have escaped with just a bump on your forehead.
もしも　刀身が七花の肉体に届いていたなら
額にこぶ程度では済みませんでしたよ
否
No.
その言葉をもって 虚刀流の名札と受け取っておくとしよう
I'll accept those words as proof of Kyotouryuu.
さようですか
Is that so?
Let's hear what you have to say then.
では　お話を伺いましょう
Alright.
そなた天下が欲しくないか？
Hey you, wouldn't you like to rule the world?
No.
いらん
Exactly.
そうであろう
それは この世に生を受けたからには当然のことだ
It's a natural desire for all who live in this world.
野心の強さを恥じることはない
There's no shame in having ambition.
かの反逆者たちの心意気そのものまでも誰が否定できよう
Who can deny the motivations of rebels?
突き詰めれば今の将軍家も
If you look into it, you'll find that even the current Shogunate were originally servants who supplanted their masters.
もともとは下克上で成り上がった家系ではないか
ならば 　…って　いらんのかい！
Which means... wait, you said "no"??
Yeah.
ああ 　あんたの話はよく分からん
I don't really get what you're saying.
Don't get it?
分からんだと
とがめさん なにぶん　わたしたちは島育ちの世間知らずです
Togame-san.
Being born and raised on this island, we don't really know about the world.
遠回しな表現は通じぬものと思っていただいた方が
It's better if you assume we don't understand wordy language.
うっ そうか
Is that right?
そうなると
In that case, could I have you leave?
七実には席を外してもらいたいのだが
I can't agree to that.
それは無理な相談だ
理由は２つある
There are two reasons why.
一つは虚刀流は血族の技だからだ
The first is that Kyotouryuu is an art inherited by blood.
たとえ親父が生きてたって
Even if dad were still here, he'd have let us stay too.
俺と姉ちゃんをこの場に同席させただろう
そしてもう一つ
And the other reason is because I'm bad at thinking.
俺は物を考えるのが苦手だ
Really? You're bad at thinking, huh.
そうか 物を考えることが苦手か
では　他言無用ということで話をさせてもらうことにしよう
Then I'll continue under the promise of confidentiality.
四季崎記紀という刀かじを知っておるな？
Do you know a swordsmith by the name of Shikizaki Kiki?
No.
知らん
Exactly.
そうであろう このような離れ小島に住んでおったところで
Even on this isolated island, any swordsman will at least have heard that name.
剣客を名乗る以上はその名を知らぬというわけにはゆくまい
刀を使わぬ虚刀流にとっては
For a school like Kyotouryuu which fights without weapons, someone like Shikizaki is a natural enemy.
四季崎は天敵のような存在になるのか
…って　知らんのかい！
Wait, you said, "no"??
Yeah.
大層なやつだということは分かった
Though I get the idea that he's a big deal.
Shikizaki Kiki...
四季崎記紀　確か戦国時代の有名な刀かじでしたか
If I recall, he was a famous swordsmith from the Sengoku period?
その程度の認識しかないのか
That's all you know about him?
虚刀流の開祖と浅からぬ因縁があったということだけは
I only heard that he had a close connection to the founder of Kyotouryuu.
聞いていますが
四季崎はどの流派にも属さない孤独にして孤高
Shikizaki didn't belong to any sword school.
He isolated himself from others, the greatest heretic of the heretical swordsmiths.
異端中の異端の刀かじ
However, it's said his swordsmithery dominated the Sengoku period.
しかし　彼こそが戦国を最も支配した刀かじといわれておる
戦国を支配？
Dominated the Sengoku period?
言葉の意味が分かりませんが
I don't understand what you mean by that...
彼はどこの国どこの家にも属さず
Belonging to no country or house, he distributed the swords he made indiscriminately throughout the land.
おのが打った刀を全国に節操なくばらまいた
Within 25 countries, he gave out a thousand swords.
総計２５カ国に合計 １，０００本の刀をだ
１，０００本 多いな
A thousand?
That's a lot!
Not very many.
少ないですね
少ないの方で
Not many then...
四季崎の刀が多い国ほど
The more of his swords a country had, the better they did on the battlefield.
優勢に戦闘を進めた
それを戦国を支配したと言わずして　何と言おう
If that's not dominating the Sengoku period, then what is?
それは逆なのでは
Couldn't you say it's the other way around?
戦闘を優位に進められるほどの大きな国だからこそ
Being large and powerful enough to hold an advantage in combat allowed some countries to amass more of his swords.
四季崎の刀を多く集めることができたのだと
確かに現実的にはそう見るべきだろう
It's true that's how it must look from a practical standpoint.
On the other hand, it's also true there's a basis for that myth.
しかし　そういう幻想が生じたこともまた確かだ
１５０年前その幻想に取りつかれた旧将軍が
They say 150 years ago, Shogun Kyuu obsessed over those mythical weapons,
and when he achieved unification of the country, he held a majority of the swords; 507 of them.
天下統一を成し遂げた際過半数５０７本の刀があったという
大人げねえ
How childish...
その後　四季崎の刀を妄信した旧将軍が行った政が
After that, Shogun Kyuu, who put all his trust in Shikizaki's swords, made that corrupt decree to collect up all swords.
かの悪法　刀狩りだ
大仏造りのためとかどうとかってやつ？
The one he said was for making a Buddha statue or something?
That was only the face of it.
それは表向きの話だ
真の目的は 剣客狩りだったと聞いています
I heard the real purpose of it was to bring together all the swordsmen into one place.
No, the true goal was—
いや 誠の目的は
"to collect together all of Shikizaki's swords"?
四季崎の刀の収集にあった
Exactly.
そのとおりだ
何ともあきれた話ですね
That's quite surprising to hear.
That said, Shogun Kyuu collected over 100,000 swords.
とはいえそれで１０万本を超える刀が旧将軍の下に集まったのだ
100,000 swords?
１０万本 少ないな
That's not very many!
多いですね
Quite a lot.
多いの方で
Quite a lot then...
で その四季崎の刀が集まったってことか
So did he collect all of Shikizaki's swords?
いや 最終的に旧将軍はあきらめたのだ
No.
He gave up at the very end.
１，０００本　全て所在までは突き止めることができていた
He managed to track down the locations of all one thousand swords...
所在まではな
but only their locations.
Shouldn't he have been able to collect them all then?
だったら収集できただろう？
He had the authority of the Shogunate after all.
将軍の権力があったんだからさ
そうは問屋が卸さんのだよこの話は
It didn't work out that way.
Among the thousand, the final 12 remaining were incredibly unique.
１，０００本のうち最後に残った１２本というのがな
どうしようもない際物でな
９８８本は
It's currently believed that the first 988 were mere practice for the purpose of creating those 12 swords.
そのたった１２本を制作するための習作だったというのが
現在の考え方だ
A thousand for the sake of 12?
１２本のための１，０００本
いい狂いっぷりであろう？
Pretty crazy story, right?
鉋
Kanna.
Plane, the Absolute
鈍
Namakura.
Blunt, the Decapitator
つるぎ
Tsurugi.
Blade, the Thousand
針
Hari.
Needle, the Light
鎧
Yoroi.
Armor, the Grudge
鎚
Kanazuchi.
Hammer, the Pair
鐚
Bita.
Poor, the Evil
釵
Kanzashi.
Sai, the Tiny
鋸
Nokogiri.
Saw, the King
銓
Hakari.
Scales, the True
镀
Mekki.
Gild, the Poison
銃
Jyuu.
Gun, the Flame
そしてそれらの凶悪さはよく聞こえた
The evilness of those swords is incomparable to any other famous sword you've heard of.
名刀妖刀などでは比較にならない
旧将軍の命で収集に出向いた軍隊が
The records say that the armies sent by Shogun Kyuu to collect them were wiped out by the power of a single sword.
ただ一本の刀に全滅させられたという記録がある
初めて聞く話です
This is the first time I've heard that.
そこでわたしがこの島にやって来た用件だ
And that is why I've come to this island.
虚刀流当主　鑢七花
Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Shichika.
伝説の刀かじ四季崎記紀が
I've come to convey this command to you, to gather the last 12 swords that the legendary swordsmith Shikizaki Kiki made.
最後の１２本　それを収集する命をそなたに与えたい
So that's what you meant when you asked if I wanted to rule the world.
天下が欲しくないかってそういう意味か
Indeed.
いかにも　別に本当にそなたが天下人になるわけではない
I didn't actually mean you would rule the world.
今の幕府は　長いこと盤石なんだろう
The Shogunate right now has been stable for a long time, right?
大乱すら力任せに押さえ付けることができるくらい強大よ
They had the power to suppress the rebellion with brute force.
そう力任せにな
Indeed, with brute force...
いや その大乱が問題だったのだ
N-No I mean, that rebellion was a problem.
尾張幕府もはや１５０年
The Owari Shogunate has been in power for 150 years now.
今となっては戦国時代を本当の意味で知っている者はいない
No one in this generation really understands what the Sengoku period was like anymore.
These days no one really thinks of Shikizaki Kiki's swords as anything more than trinkets, but just think about it...
四季崎の刀も 今やお守り程度にしか考えられてはいなかったろう
が 考えてもみるがよい
If the conspirators behind the last rebellion had gotten a hold of those 12 swords,
もしも　先の大乱の首謀者が
こぞって１２本の刀の持ち主だったなら
what would have happened to the current Shogunate?
現幕府とてどうなっていたものか
They fear a revolt...
幕府は反乱を恐れている
"You can never be too careful" kind of thing?
念には念をってことか
So where are those swords currently?
それで　刀の所在は？
分かっているものは　因幡 出雲 薩摩 蝦夷 土佐
The ones we know of are in Inaba, Izumo, Satsuma, Ezo, and Tosa.
残りは調査中
The rest are still under investigation.
You only know where half of them are...
半分しか分かっていないとは
Say "you've already found half of them" instead!
「半分も分かっている」と言ってくれ
What is it?
何だ
If they're afraid of a revolt, wouldn't it be smarter not to provoke the current owners?
反乱が怖いんだったら変に
今の持ち主を刺激しない方がいいんじゃないのか
"Do it skillfully" was the order given by the Shogunate.
「うまくやれ」というのが幕府からのお達しだ
What does doing it skillfully mean?
どううまくやれっていうんだよ
そのために奇策士がいる
We have a strategian for that very purpose!
わたしのように裏で動く人間がな
Someone who can move about in the shadows.
あの
Um...
奇策士って　何なのですか？
What exactly is a "strategian"?
正確には
Specifically, I'm the army general director in support of critical tasks under direct control of Yanari Shogun of the Owari Shogunate,
尾張幕府家鳴将軍直轄預奉所軍所総監督
奇策士　とがめだ
the strategian Togame.
えっと この２０年の間に新しくできた役職か何かで？
Um...
Is that a new post that was created in the last 20 years or something?
No, I just made up that title.
いや これはわたしが勝手に名乗っているだけだ
Self-named...
自称かよ
If tactics are created by a tactician, strategies are created by a strategian!
策を練るのが策士なら
奇策を練るのが奇策士だ
普通ではない命令は普通でないわたしのところに下りるのだ
I'm abnormal, so abnormal orders are given to me.
そんなわけで　わたしに協力してはくれまいか？
That being the case, can you lend me your strength?
If you're really from the Shogunate, there's no need for you to rely on Kyotouryuu...
あんたが幕府の人間だっていうんなら
別に虚刀流に頼らなくてもいくらでも
I know what you're trying to say.
言わんとしていることは分かるが
However, I can't use people who will work for money.
金で動く人間は駄目だ
The ninja who were entrusted the task of collecting the swords...
収集を依頼した忍者が
裏切ったのだ
betrayed us.
忍者なのにですか
Even though they're ninja?
Your surprise is understandable.
その驚きは分かるぞ
If they did that, the trust in them that they'd built up over all those years would collapse.
そんなことをすれば
長年築き上げてきた信用もがた落ちだからな
Even so, once they found the swords, they disappeared.
しかしそれでも　やつらは刀を持ったまま姿を消したのだ
The entire ninja army, along with their whole village.
忍軍丸ごと里もろともだ
Unbelievable...
とんでもないことを
完成形変体刀は１本で国が買える価値を持つ高級芸術品だ
The perfected Deviant Blades are such a high class treasure that you could buy an entire country with the cost of a single sword.
金で動く人間は駄目だ
That's why people who'd work for money are unacceptable.
I see.
なるほど じゃあ名誉はどうだ？
Then how about honor?
剣士はかくあるべきだと俺は親父に教えられたぞ
My father taught me that swordsmen should do what's right.
Honor, huh...
名誉か 剣士も駄目だ
Swordsmen are no good either.
幕府が知る中で最も強く最も忠義に厚い剣客を１人選んだ
The Shogunate picked one of their strongest, most loyal and honorable swordsmen.
名を錆白兵といってな
His name was Sabi Hakuhei.
They tasked him with retrieving what they thought was the hardest sword to obtain - Hakutou Hari.
最も手に入れるのが困難だろうと思われた薄刀針を
きゃつは驚くべき短時間で手に入れた
However, he obtained it in a shockingly short time.
Wow!
He obtained it, then disappeared.
手に入れて失踪したのだ
Hey!
毒が強過ぎるのだ
It's poison was too strong.
名誉で動く剣士だからこそ
And he betrayed us precisely because of that honor — he was unable to resist the honor of owning one of Shikizaki's swords.
四季崎の刀を所持する名誉からは逃れられなかったのであろう
Ninja and swordsmen...
忍者に剣士と
So the swords are now in the possession of really strong guys...
より強いやつのところに刀が移ったわけだ
あんたの信用がた落ちだわ
Your followers must all be running away.
That's right!
そうなのだ 何とかならんものか
What can I do about it?
Like I'd know!
知るか
So that's why you sought out Kyotouryuu.
それで　虚刀流ですか
Swordsmen who don't work for money nor wield swords.
金で動かず刀を使わない剣士であること
そうだ
Exactly.
虚刀流当主　鑢七花
Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Shichika!
In order to ensure the prosperity of the Owari Shogunate, will you wield the skills you have forged?
尾張幕府１，０００年の歴史のために
研さんしたその技術を使ってはくれぬか
I understand what you came for,
話は分かったけどよ
それはあんたには必要って話で俺は特に刀ってやつにも関心がねえ
and it sounds urgent for you, but I don't have any interest in swords.
怖いのか
Are you scared?
Of course I am!
そりゃ怖いよ けれどもそれ以上に面倒だ
But more importantly, it's a hassle, leaving the island and crossing the sea and all.
わざわざ海を渡って出向くほどじゃない
その答え　このわたしが予想しなかったと思うか
Do you think I didn't anticipate that answer?
幾度となく煮え湯を飲まされてきたこの奇策士が
Do you believe that this strategian who has been betrayed so many times in the past,
came to this island without preparing an appropriate reason for you?
そなたごときを動かすのに足る理由も持たずに
この島にやって来たと思ったか
煮え湯を飲んできたんですね
You've been betrayed, have you?
Well do you have one? A reason?
何かあんのかよ理由
Yeah.
金で動く人間は駄目だ
People who work for money are no good.
People who work for honor are also no good.
名誉で動く人間も駄目だった
That leaves only one reason.
ならば残された理由はたった一つ
愛だ
Love!
愛？
L-Love?
People who work for love can be trusted.
愛で動く人間は信用できる
鑢七花 わたしにほれていいぞ
Yasuri Shichika...
fall for me!
手裏剣？
Shuriken?!
What the hell!
ふざけんな！
This is the home dad built!
親父が建てた家だぞ
Shichika...
七花
Honestly, so hasty...
まったく　何て短絡的な
No, that was the right thing to do.
いや あれで正解だ
飛び道具に関しては即断即決しかない
For aerial weaponry, you have to make split-second decisions.
まあ 本能で動いていますからね
Well, he's just moving on instinct...
A ninja... from the Maniwa corps, it seems.
忍者 真庭忍軍だな
Maniwa?
真庭？
The ones who turned traitor the instant they learned of the value of Shikizaki's swords.
四季崎の刀の価値を知った途端裏切ったやつらだ
How many are there?
何人でしょうか？
Probably just one.
１人であろうな
真庭の忍びは集団行動を嫌う
Maniwa ninja hate working in groups.
分からんのは どうしてやつらがここにということだ
What I don't know is why they're here...
尾行されるわけなどないし
I wasn't tailed, and I didn't tell anyone my destination.
行く先は誰にも告げてないのに
If the enemy is really here alone,
敵が本当に１人ならおそらく
この先の砂浜に七花は相手を誘導しているはずです
then Shichika is probably leading them to the beach ahead.
You seem pretty confident.
ずいぶんな自信だな
敵は真庭忍軍だぞ
The enemy is from the Maniwa corps, you know?
忍者ごときに後れを取る虚刀流ではありません
Kyotouryuu won't lose to a mere ninja.
That's reassuring, but what's most important right now is why is a Maniwa corps soldier is on the island!
頼もしいかぎりだが
今は真庭忍軍の者が
どうしてここにいるのかを事項だ考える方が圧倒的優先
That's true...
それはそうですね
とがめさん 尾行されていた可能性は本当にないのですか
Togame-san, are you certain there was no possibility you were followed?
Don't insult me.
くどいな
相手が忍者だからこそ これ以上ないくらい警戒を払ったのだ
It was precisely because the opponent is a ninja that I was more cautious than usual.
That's also why I didn't tell anyone my destination.
行く先を　誰にも告げなかったのもそのためだ
本当にどうして？
I really wonder how...
Did you come to this island alone?
あの　とがめさんはこの島に１人で来られたんですか
You're seriously asking that?
何をいまさら
では　どうやって来ましたか
How did you get here then?
I came by boat, of course!
舟で来たに決まっておる
自分で舟をこいだのですか
Did you row the boat yourself?
異なことを言う わたしは頭脳労働が専門なのだ
What a strange question.
My specialty is brain work.
Does it look like I'd have the strength to—
そんな力があるように見える
So there was a ferryman?
船頭がいたのでは？
いや しかし
Yes, but...
Oh no!
まずい！
そいつは四季崎の刀を持っている！
That man wields one of Shikizaki's swords!
I hope you're not thinking you've driven me into a corner.
お前はひょっとしちゃって
この俺を追い詰めたつもりになってんじゃねえだろうな
It's the opposite!
逆だぜ逆
I'm the one who led you here!
俺がお前をここまで誘導したんだっつうの
Wait, wait...
待て　待て
My head is spinning from all the visitors here today.
今日は客が多くて 頭が混乱しているんだ
Could you not all come on the same day like this?
そう１日に何人も来るな
はあ？お前の都合なんか知るかよ
I don't give a damn about your problems.
I'm one of the 12 heads of the Maniwa corps, the great Maniwa Koumori!
俺は真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人真庭蝙蝠さまだ
Maniwa corps?
真庭忍軍？
Oh yeah, I heard you're a ninja or something.
ああ さっき忍者がどうとか聞いたな
The fact that you heard that is bad luck for you.
その聞いてしまったのが運の尽きだ
If it weren't for that, I'd have just ignored you.
それさえなきゃ　逃がしてやってもよかったんだがな
My objective is that woman who has all that information.
俺の目的はあの女がしゃべる情報の方にあったんだからよ
You were eavesdropping?
盗み聞きしてたのか
That's a poor hobby.
趣味が悪いな
You should say it's a good hobby!
趣味がいいと言ってくれ
とがめの後をつけてきたのか
You tailed Togame here?
Nope.
いいや そんなこそこそしたまねはしねえ
I didn't do anything so sneaky.
We came here together.
一緒に来たのよ
I rowed the boat all the way here.
ギーコラバッタン舟をこいでな
It was hard work you know.
しんどかったぜ
That woman just sat on her ass the whole time without lifting a finger to help.
あの女偉そうにふんぞり返って 手伝おうともしねえんだからよ
Does everyone from the mainland talk as much as this?
She's got quite the nerve, geez...
本土の人間ってのはどいつもこいつもこんなにしゃべるのか
Don't you think so?
なっ　そう思うだろ？
Right...
You're a pretty dull guy.
ノリの悪いやつ
Well, you are from the boonies I guess...
まっ　田舎者だしなしゃあねえか
Can't help that.
It's nothing personal, but I'll have to kill you now.
お前に　恨みはねえけどぶっ殺させてもらうぜ
Come to think of it, this is my first real battle, isn't it?
そういえば　実戦は初めてか
You scared?
おびえてんのか
いや 見たところ刀も持ってないようだし
No...
I was just thinking you aren't carrying a sword, as far as I can tell...
Oh right, you're a swordsman who doesn't use a sword?
ああ そういや刀を使わない剣士なんだって
When it comes to "swordsmanship" you usually assume you're going to be fighting with swords.
剣術ってのは普通　刀を相手に想定するもんだからな
バカげた剣術もあったもんだぜ
That's some ridiculously absurd swordsmanship!
Not really, it's just that I don't know much about how ninja fight.
別に
ただ 俺が忍者についてよく知らないってことだ
Don't worry.
安心しなよ 　確かに俺は剣士じゃねえが
While I'm not a swordsman, it's not like I can't use a sword.
しかし刀は使えないわけじゃない
As you wish, how about I bring out the sword I'm carrying?
ご要望にお応えして
取って置きの刀をいきなし使ってやろうじゃねえか
What?
何だ！？
Humans can do something like that?
人間ってそんなことができたのか
Listen and look in shock!
聞いて驚け　見て驚け
This is one of the 12 Deviant Blades that Shikizaki Kiki perfected, Zettou Kanna!
これが
四季崎記紀が完成形変体刀十二本が一本 絶刀　鉋だ！
Kanna
Zettou
I'm more shocked at your body than the sword...
刀以上にあんたの体に驚きだ
They call me Hades Koumori!
俺の通り名は冥土の蝙蝠
Meaning, I have a very generous personality when it comes to serving up presents from hell!
冥土の土産をあまりにも大盤振る舞いする
接待好きの性格ってわけだ
Koumori the maid?
メードの蝙蝠
That sounds strangely cute...
不思議とカワイイ感じがするんだが
Stop spouting such nonsense!
訳分かんねえこと言ってんじゃねえよ
That aside, aren't you feeling anything right now?
それより　お前何か感想はねえのか
This is one of the Shikizaki swords that that woman was talking about earlier, you know.
さっきあの女が散々語っていた四季崎の刀だぜ
うん 何かねえのかよ
Nothing at all?
I don't really want to take it when it's all sticky like that.
べとべとになっちゃってるのはいただけないな
あん？
It's really valuable, right?
貴重品なんだろ
Should you really be carrying it around like that?
そんなふうに持ち歩いてていいのかよ？
Quite the opposite.
逆だ逆
If I didn't keep it stored inside my body, I'd be worried about the safety of such a valuable treasure.
肌身離さず身に着けてねえとこんな高価なもん
不安でしょうがねえっつうの
それに　こいつには不思議な魅力があるぜ
On top of that, this thing has an interesting power.
あの女は毒っつってたけど こいつはとんだ百薬の長だ
That woman called it poison, but this thing is the ultimate medicine!
When you hold it, you feel it's desire to cut off people's heads!
所有すると人を斬ってみたくなる
Houfuku Zettou!
報復絶刀！
Houfuku
Zettou
Kyotouryuu, first dance: Lily of the Valley.
虚刀流一の構え
鈴蘭
Then how about this?
じゃあ　こういうのはどうよ
Houfuku Zettou!
報復絶刀
Kyotouryuu: Chrysanthemum!
虚刀流　菊
Huh?
あれ！？
You little...
てめえ　俺が見えて
You saw through—
You're so noisy!
騒ぎ過ぎだ
礼を言うぜ　虚刀流
Let me thank you.
It's been a long time since I've been surprised by anyone.
久しぶりにびっくり仰天ってやつを体験させてもらった
You use your arms and legs as swords...
手刀や足刀を駆使するわけか
You know your stuff, I guess you really are a swordsman.
種が知れりゃ確かに剣士ではあるわな
I'm not nearly as surprising as you though.
あんたのびっくり人間ぶりほどじゃねえさ
Nor...
それに　その鉋ほどでもな
as surprising as that "Kanna".
Did you notice anything from that attack?
さっきの一合で
何か気付いたのか
The technique I just used isn't meant to catch swords.
さっきのあれ剣を受け止める技じゃねえんだ
Kyotouryuu: Chrysanthemum is a technique that breaks your opponent's sword in two.
虚刀流菊は 相手の刀を真っ二つにする技だ
That sword is definitely weird.
その刀絶対変だぞ
何かと思えば
What are you talking about?
Of course it's weird!
変も変さ 変でねえ方がおかしいっつうの
If would be strange if it didn't seem weird.
This Zettou Kanna was created with toughness as its main focus.
この絶刀鉋はな
頑丈さに主眼に置いて作られた刀なんだよ
Swords are expendable, so when you use them they'll break or bend and lose their ability to cut.
刀なんざ消耗品だから使ってりゃ
折れるし曲がるしよく斬れなくなっちまう
However, this Kanna is different.
ところがこの鉋は違う 本当に折れないし本当に曲がらないし
It can't ever be broken or bent.
That's why it always cuts so well.
だからこそいつまでもよく斬れるのさ
Wow...
Even though it's a straight sword, no matter what you do it doesn't chip.
こいつは　直刀でありながら
何をしたって刃こぼれ一つ起きねえんだ
象が踏んでも壊れない日本刀
It's a Japanese sword that wouldn't break even if elephants trampled it.
It'd sell for a really high price too!
こいつは高く売れちゃうぜ
I did some research and found out...
俺の調べた話じゃ
Even though that Shikizaki geezer was a swordsmith, he also dabbled in the occult and alchemy.
四季崎ってじじいは刀かじでありながら
陰陽道や錬金術やらにも手を出していたらしいからな
Rather suspicious methods, don't you think?
怪しい術でも使ってたんじゃねえの？
A guy who pulls swords out of his mouth like you is 12 times more suspicious.
口から刀を取り出すお前の方が十二分に怪しいよ
There was a reason for that little story.
ところで
ということはだぜ
虚刀流ってのは四季崎の刀にはかなわないってことだよな
You must now understand that Kyotouryuu cannot match up to Shikizaki's swords.
Your sword-breaking technique couldn't break it after all!
刀を折る技で折れなかったんだからな
I see that Kyotouryuu aims to destroy the opponent's weapons.
虚刀流ときたら相手の武器の破壊をもくろんじゃうなんてな
Really, that's outstanding!
いやはやずばぬけてるよ
I would have loved to see you do it though!
しかしできれば見て驚きたかったところだよな
Kyotouryuu, second dance: Daffodil.
虚刀流二の構え
水仙
This time I will definitely shatter that Zettou Kanna.
今度はきっちりその絶刀鉋とやらをへし折ってやるよ
Idiot!
バカ！
What do you mean shatter it?!
折ってどうする折って!
If I brought it like that to the Shogunate, they'd make me commit harakiri!
そんなもの幕府に差し出したら腹を切らされるわ！
Ah...
Didn't you listen to a single word I was saying?
そなたは　人の話を何一つ聞いてなかったのか
It's not like I said I'd accept your request anyway...
別に　俺はあんたの頼み事を引き受けるとは言ってないのだが
That's not the problem here!
そういう問題ではないわ
Don't you understand the value of things?
お前には物の価値が分からないのか
That's right!
そのとおりだな
お金になるもんをぶっ壊しちゃうだなんて
As one who understands the value of things, smashing something of monetary worth is unthinkable to me.
物の価値が分かっちゃう俺には 絶対にできねえ行為だよ
Yep.
How about I start off with this?
取りあえずはこう言っておこうか
It's been a while, little kitty.
久しぶりだな　小猫ちゃん
真庭蝙蝠
Maniwa Koumori...
Don't be so mad.
そう怒るなよ
忍者ってのは
Ninja may be traitors, but sneakiness is our selling point.
裏切るもんだろうがひきょう卑劣が売りなんだからよ
Why you...
貴様！
We'll have plenty of time to talk about that later, Miss Strategian.
その辺の話は 後で　ゆっくりさせてもらうぜ
奇策士さん
Nice and slowly, after I destroy this Kyotouryuu guy!
この虚刀流をぶっ殺してから　ゆっくりとな
Shichika, defeat him!
七花！　そいつを倒せ！
Actually, that Kanna has got me riled up.
取りあえず　あの鉋ってのには興味が湧いたぜ
Like I said, don't break it!
いや だから刀は壊すな
Yeah, yeah.
分かった分かった ついでに要望があれば言ってくれ
If you have any other requests, say so now.
I'm going to end this right now.
びしっと応えてやるから
Well, in that case...
ではそうだな できるだけ派手な技を使ってくれ
If at all possible, do it with a flashy move.
I'll have to hand in a report describing how we obtained the sword.
刀を手に入れた経緯は 報告書にして提出しなければならぬからな
If you have some cool move that'll capture the reader's attention, I'll ask that you use it now!
読者の興味をそそるようなカッコイイ技があるなら
ここはひとつそれを頼む
Once again, don't destroy that sword, even accidentally.
繰り返すが
間違っても刀を破壊してくれるな
If you do, this story will end at chapter one!
そんなことをされては
第１話で話が終わってしまう
Chapter one? Are you writing a book?
第１話って　本でも書くつもりかよ？
I'd also like to do that sometime in the future.
将来的にはそれもいいな
It'd sell!
売れるぞ
I guess I'll show you something flashy then.
んじゃ　派手なやつ見せてやるよ
Sorry to keep you waiting, Koumori.
待たせたな　蝙蝠
Wha... hey!
って　おい！
No no, it was me delaying this.
いやいや こちらこそ待たせた
What are you doing?
何しまってるんだ！
It's not going to be much of a fight like that!
それじゃ勝負にならないだろうが
Yep.
うむ 　俺は剣士じゃないからな
I'm not a swordsman, after all.
I'm particular about this sword, so being beaten by you here wouldn't be very shinobi of me.
変に刀にこだわってお前に倒されんのも忍びねえ
Oops, was that a pun?
おっと！？　駄じゃれになっちまったか
構わねえよ どっちみち倒す
I don't care.
I'll beat you either way.
You're no match for me if I fight with ninjutsu.
忍術で対抗していいんならお前なんざ相手にはならねえよ
My actual battlefield experience is on a different level from yours.
経験が違う 実戦経験がな
ここまでのは接待だ
So far this has just been a welcoming reception.
Just think of it as a bad habit of mine.
冥土の蝙蝠のただの悪い癖だったと思え
I'm going to be serious from now on.
ここから先はガチでいっちゃうぜ
Stop screwing around!
ふざけるな！
それは貴様の唾液で汚していいような代物ではないぞ
That thing isn't just a decoration for you to get your drool all over!
Take it out! Take it out right now!
吐き出せ　今すぐに吐き出せ
Geez, such a noisy little kitty.
あー　もううっせえ小猫ちゃんだな
Fine...
分かったよ
Oh? You're unexpectedly cooperati—
何だ 思いのほか素直だ…
くっ 　痛え
Ow...
Huh?
あれ！？
Damn, that was close.
ったく　もうヤベえヤベえ
That kid is really something.
あの小僧超とんでもねえってえの
Though I was expecting something like that, little kitty.
まっ何かあっちゃうとは思っていたがな 小猫ちゃん
うっ　何だこれは
What's this?
Oh, you're awake?
目を覚ましたか？
Don't worry, I'll be killing you soon.
安心しな やるのはこれからだよ
Koumori!!
蝙蝠
You probably think you've found something good,
あんた　確かに目の付けどころは良かったみたいだけど
but that's too naive!
甘いよ
He may be used to battling, but he's never been on a battlefield.
あいつ　戦闘向きかもしれないが戦場向きじゃねえ
ふん 逃げ出した臆病者が
You're just a coward who runs away.
Hey hey, what are you blabbing about?
おいおいおい 何ほざいてんだ
力に対して策で挑むのが
Isn't a wise person supposed to fight strength using intellect, Miss Strategian?
賢き者のすることだな 奇策士さん
All you do is bully weaker people!
貴様のは　弱き者をなぶっているだけだ
I come up with strategies that allow the weak to challenge the strong, by whittling away their life and spirit.
わたしの奇策は弱き者が強き者にかみつくために考えだす
命と魂を削るやり方だ
一緒にするな げすが
Don't even compare us, you lowlife!
I see strategians are also good at running their mouths off.
奇策士ってのはへ理屈もうまいもんだ
それにしてもあのせりふはないだろ
Though even so, that's not what you did, is it?
What?
"Fall for me"?
「わたしにほれていいぞ」って
おいおい すげえこと言ってるよな
Come on, that's pretty wild!
I was so surprised I accidentally spat out those shuriken.
びっくりして思わず手裏剣砲撃っちまったじゃねえか
That attack wasn't intentional?
あの砲撃は思わずなのか
It was way too embarrassing for me to bear.
恥ずかしさのあまりこらえきれなくてな
That's touching, I'd have liked someone to say that to me.
甘酸っぱいね 俺もそう言ってほしかったね そういうこと
まっ　欲しい情報は全部聞いたしなちょうどよかったよ
Well I overheard all the information I needed, so it's fine.
さっさと殺せ！
Hurry up and kill me!
Stop trying to act so dignified, little kitty.
潔いふりなんてしてんじゃねえよ小猫ちゃん
Even though you say that, you're trying to think of a way to outsmart me, right?
そう言いながら腹ん中では俺を出し抜く方法を色々考えてんだろ
You're even trickier than I am.
あんたの腹ん中は俺以上に混沌としてるぜ
Don't worry, I won't kill you.
安心しろ 殺したりしねえよ
さっきの手裏剣砲だって　わざと外してやったんだぜ
I deliberately missed with that shuriken attack earlier.
You don't understand the concept of moderation do you?
貴様は加減を知るのだな
If one had even nicked me, I would have died!
かすったりしようものならわたしは死んでいたぞ
You don't know how fragile I am.
わたしのひ弱さを貴様は知らない
That's not something you should be bragging about!
自慢するみたいに言うことじゃねえっつうの
戻ったら拷問するんだからよ 少しは頑張ってくれよな
I'll torture you when I return, so bear with it a little longer.
I'm sure you're not completely clueless about the location of the remaining swords.
残りの刀の在りかだってまったく情報がないわけじゃないんだろ
Though, since this is the end I guess I'll ask you.
最後に一応誘っといてやるぜ
How about turning your back on the Shogunate and following us?
あんた幕府なんざ裏切って俺らと組んじゃわないか
I'll be sure to give you a piece of the action.
分け前はちゃんと計算してやる
I decline.
断る
People who work for money can't be trusted.
金で動くやつは信用できない
You're afraid of being betrayed?
裏切ったことを怒ってんのか
I'd say it's more strange to trust in a ninja.
忍者を信用しちゃう方がおかしいってよ
Now then...
あっ　さて
I'm sure you've been thinking it, but the truth is you're not actually a hostage.
色々考えたけど 実際あんたじゃ人質にならないわけよ
How about this?
そこでこういうのはどうだ
What if I changed my appearance to that of your's?
俺の姿が変わっていたらそれがあんたの姿だったら
This way even that Kyotouryuu guy will let down his guard.
さすがの虚刀流も油断するだろうぜ
You must be aware of my ability, right?
俺の能力を知らないわけじゃないだろ
After all, I found Kanna under your orders, then stole it.
あんたの命令で鉋を奪ってきたんだからな
虚刀流をぶっ殺したら
After I kill that Kyotouryuu guy, maybe I'll transform into him to kill you.
今度はその虚刀流に化けてお姉ちゃんをぶっ殺すとするか
Sorry, but I'll have you wait there until then.
悪いけど あんたはそれまでここで待っといてくれ
待て
Wait!
I originally betrayed you for money,
俺が裏切ったのは金のためだが
but even were it not for that, if i had known what kind of person you were from the start, I wouldn't have worked with you.
そうでなくともあんたがどんな人間かを最初から知っていたら
そもそも組みさえしなかったろうよ
Even that invitation just now was just so I could work with you again,
さっき誘ってやったのもあんたと組んで
もう一度裏切ってやるためだ
and then betray you again.
There's no one in this world who'd stay by your side.
あんたを好きになるやつなんざこの世にはいない
That's strange...
おかしいなぁ
Where on earth did they go?
あいつら　どこへ行ったんだ
Leave the island, huh...
島を出るか いまさら
This late...
What a hassle.
めんどくさい
It's true that Kyotouryuu is a particularly troublesome opponent against Shikizaki's Deviant Blades.
確かに四季崎の変体刀にとって
虚刀流は最も嫌な相手だ
I'll have to make use of this chance to kill him.
この殺せる機会を生かさせてもらわねえとな
He's dead for sure. It's too bad...
確実に殺せる
惜しいなぁ
Well, once that woman set her eyes on him, his luck had already run out.
まっ あの女に目を付けられたことが
すでについてなかったためだが
Here I go.
行くか
The premise is I barely escaped with my life from captivity.
設定は拉致されたものの命からがら自力で脱出してきた
Before he can say anything, embrace him...
有無を言わせず抱き付いて
And then kill.
そして　殺す
Shichika!
七花
Kyotouryuu: Peony!
虚刀流　牡丹
Kyotouryuu
Peony
えっ！？何で？
Why?!
What was wrong? The disguise?
何が違った？
変装？
No, this isn't even a disguise, my transformation was perfect!
いや 俺のこれは変装なんかじゃねえ
変身は完ぺきだろ
うん よく見りゃとがめじゃねえか
Now that I look, it's Togame?
This guy...
こいつ　誰と分からずに技を出したのか
He used that technique without even knowing who I was?!
Huh?
あれ ってことは　お前 蝙蝠の方か？方？
Wait, then I guess you're Koumori?
Guess?
おま お前相手が誰だか認識できてないのか
Y-You...
Can't you even recognize who you're facing?!
Well, today's the first time I've ever seen another human besides Nee-chan.
いや姉ちゃん以外の人間なんて今日初めて見たようなもんだからな
I can't recognize faces that quickly.
すぐには見分けがつかん
What the hell?
何だと？
This wasn't even a question of disguise!
変装以前の問題だ
From the beginning, this guy couldn't even differentiate between people?
こいつはなから 人の区別がついてなかった
That was close...
ヤベえな 　あいつの方だったら死んでたよな
If it was her, she'd have died.
This is beyond boonies...
田舎者どころの話じゃねえ けだものが
This guy's an animal!
She asked for a flashy move, but it turned out kind of boring.
派手な技といわれていたが地味になっちまったな
You...
お前 お前はそんなにこの女の役に立ちたいのか？
Do you really want to help that woman so badly?
I'm asking if you want to be used by her!
この女に利用されたいのかと聞いてる
Used?
利用？
Didn't you think there was something strange about her story?
お前はこいつの話を聞いて おかしいと思わなかったのか
Why does the Shogunate suddenly want to collect Shikizaki's swords after all this time?
どうして幕府がいまさら四季崎の刀を集めるのか
That was... because they fear a revolt?
それは　反乱を恐れてだっけ
That is indeed a reason.
それは理由としては正しいだろう 正しいだろうぜ
Correct, however...
don't you think it sounds too convenient?
だが　少し聞こえが良過ぎるなぁ そうは思わなかったか
The Shogunate today doesn't hold the same reverence for Shikizaki's swords as Shogun Kyuu did.
今の幕府は旧将軍ほど四季崎の刀の幻想にとらわれちゃいないさ
They're far more pragmatic.
もっと現実的だ
Ultimately, collecting up the swords this time is just a means for that woman to gain recognition.
しょせん今回の刀集めなんてのはな
この女の出世のための手段にすぎないんだよ
Togame the strategian...
奇策士とがめ 軍所総監督殿の
It's nothing but a move on her part to gain fame within the army as general director.
手柄話の一つとするために行われていることにすぎないんだ
I don't really understand that recognition stuff,
出世とかは俺にはよく分からん
but isn't general director of the army already pretty high up?
軍所総監督って時点でそこそこ偉いんじゃないのか
That woman isn't satisfied with the power she has.
そんなそこそこじゃこの女は満足しねえんだよ
She's aiming for the top.
上り詰めないとな
Don't you know what it means to doubt someone?
疑うってことを知らないのか
That young woman will use any dirty tactics she needs to rise to the top of the system.
この若さの女が一組織の頂点に立つまでに
汚いまねをしてねえわけがないだろうが
Raw strength isn't everything in this world.
実力だけが物を言う世界なんてそうそうねえんだよ
When we first met, she terrified me.
初めて会ったとき俺はぞっとしたもんだぜ
There is ambition in her eyes.
この女の目に宿っていた野心にな
You can sense her willingness to sacrifice anyone and anything for her goals.
何を犠牲にしても 誰を犠牲にしても構わないって感じだった
She was perfectly willing to use the Maniwa corps, too.
真庭忍軍のことも利用する気満々だった
A fearsome ninja brigade made up of professional assassins, you know? Madness!
恐るべき暗殺専門の忍者集団真庭忍軍をだぜ
ぶっとんでるっつうの
And she is merely using you too, Kyotouryuu head!
お前も利用されるだけだ 虚刀流
Is it going to end here?
こんなことで終わってしまうのか？
こんな所で
In this place?
So before you were betrayed, you betrayed others?
で あんたは裏切られる前に　裏切ったのか
That's right.
そうさ こんな女ついていけるわけねえだろ
There's no way I'd follow that woman.
Where do you think her ultimate aim lies?
この女の最終目標ってどこだと思う？
The right hand of the Shogun!
次代将軍の　おそば人だよ
The current Shogun is getting old.
現将軍はもう年だ
It won't be long before he retires.
遠からず引退するだろうよ
When that happens, I'm sure you can imagine what the natural step will be for the young lieutenant at his side?
そうなったとき
まだ若い新将軍のおそば人であるということがどういうことか
分かるよな
Ruling the world...
天下…
I threw away my name and my family, all for it to end on this island?
名を捨て
家を捨て
こんな島で終わってしまうのか
That's not really something to condemn her for...
それは何も責められるようなことではないだろ
Well, for someone like you who was used, I'm sure it doesn't feel right.
利用されてたあんたらにしてみりゃ
確かにいい気分じゃないだろうけどさ
I don't really care about being used.
利用されんのは別にいいさ
Being used and using others is the way of the world.
利用し利用されんのは世の常だ
However, my problem in this case is the reason I was used!
ただな 利用される理由がこの場合は問題なんだよ
In case you don't know, my head isn't that great, so saying stuff like that doesn't really get through to me.
言っとくけど俺は頭が悪いから
そんな言い方じゃ何も伝わらないぞ
けっ この女はな 先の大乱の首謀者
That woman is the daughter of the leader of the last rebellion, Hida Takahito!
飛騨鷹比等の娘だ
Who can deny the motivations of rebels?
かの反逆者たちの心意気そのものまで　誰が否定できよう
If things had gone better, she'd have been the princess in her castle, ruling over a whole country.
世が世なら
一国一城のお姫さまってわけだ
I can already see it.
もう見えていた
It's within my grasp!
もう 手の届く位置だったのに
That woman is aiming for promotion without a care for the means.
そんな女が　なりふり構わず出世を狙ってんだ
She aims to be the right hand man to the current Shogun.
次代将軍のおそば人を狙ってんだ
どういうことか分かるよな？
I'm sure you understand what that means.
Father's dreams...
父さまの思念を
父さまの無念を
Father's regrets...
She was willing to ask for help from her father's enemies to collect those swords?
あいつは自分の父親の敵に刀集めを頼もうとしていたのか
It must be clear to you by now what she's planning...
何をたくらんでるかなんて明瞭だろ
Revenge!
復讐だ！
I should have been able to avenge father's death!
父さまの無念を晴らすことができたのに
It's revenge for having her whole family exterminated!
一族を根絶やしにされた意趣返しだよな
After all, that girl was watching as her family was killed!
何せあの女
てめえの家族が殺されてくさまをその目で見てたんだってよ
Even if that was the only possibility, to ask the person responsible for my father's death...
いくらそれしかなかったとはいえ
父さまを殺した張本人に
Even if not that, to depend on his son...
そうでなくてもその息子なんかに頼るなんて
Even though I'm the son of her enemy...
俺だって敵の息子だ
Maybe I was wrong to rely on Kyotouryuu after all...
やはり虚刀流に頼ろうとしたのが間違いだった
She's an insect born from the leader of the rebellion.
賊軍の出身の獅子身中の虫けらによ
I don't want to hear about treachery or cowardice from her!
裏切りがどうとか卑怯がどうとか言われたくねえってえの
This is a good body.
いい体だ
Allow me to use it as a reference.
参考にさせてもらったぜ
Your strength, musculature, and balance are all a perfect fit.
筋力から腕力から脚力からまったく互角
Though,
おっと 手裏剣砲で腕やら痛めてるから
you've got the pain from when my shuriken hit your arms and legs, so I have a bit of an advantage.
俺の方がちっとばかし有利って感じかな
Just so you know, an attack like that doesn't hurt or even itch anymore.
言っとくけどこの程度今はもう痛くもかゆくもねえ
Seems it, so I guess we're as equal as rock vs rock.
だろうよ だから まあ互角として グーとグーのあいこだとして
Though my "rock" here is quite strong.
これで　俺が強いグーだ
Hey.
なあ そのとがめの秘密を知ってるのはほかにもいるのか
Is there anyone else who knows Togame's secret?
There's no way I'd just give away such intriguing information.
こんな飛びっ切りの情報簡単に漏らすかよ
So it'll be fine if I just finish you off here, right?
じゃあ　あんたをきっちり倒せば　それでいいんだな
You're suddenly in a fighting mood now that you're facing me?
何で俺に対して士気高揚しちゃってんの
I am the 7th generation Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Shichika.
虚刀流　七代目当主　鑢七花 推して参る
Here I go!
Don't try to act cool!
キャハ！カッコつけてんじゃねえよ
Come!
こい　飛び切り派手なのを決めてやる
I'll finish you with an extremely flashy move!
Ultimate secret technique!
最終奥義
Houfuku Zettou!
報復絶刀
なっ 何で
Wh-Why?!
Kyotouryuu men don't have any skill whatsoever with a sword!
虚刀流の人間ってのは
代々剣術の才能がこれっぽっちもねえんだよ
We're not swordsmen who don't use swords,
刀を使わない剣士なんじゃない
we're swordsmen who can't use them!
刀を使えない剣士なんだ
この俺が
I'm going to be...
Incidentally, I called it "ultimate secret technique",
ちなみに最終奥義とか言ったけどさ それは何でかってえと
but the reason it sounds so generic is because it's an ultimate move I only came up with yesterday!
これは　俺が昨日考えたばかりの必殺技だからだ
The opponent take 7 hits from this secret technique, getting ripped apart in the blink of an eye!
必殺の奥義を一気に７つ食らわせ
一瞬で相手を八つ裂きにするところから
Kyouka
Suigetsu
取りあえず　こう名付けてみた
So for now, I'll call it:
Kachou
Fuugetsu
Hyakka
Ryouran
Ryuuryoku
Kakou
H
i
k
a
R
k
u
y
o
u
Kinjou
Tenka
Rakka
Rouzeki
Kyotouryuu: Shichika Hachiretsu!
虚刀流　七花八裂！
Shichika Hachiretsu
What a state I'm in now...
何というありさま
And I'm from a samurai bloodline too!
それでも武門の娘か
Before my appearance becomes any more embarrassing, I've got to...
これ以上恥をさらす前に自分で
It's not like this rope can't loosen or unravel...
ほどけず緩まないのはこんな縄じゃない
It's my strategies that are infallible and sharp!
折れず曲がらずよく切れるのはわたしの奇策だ
There's no way I can lose to this!
これしきの逆境など
So that's where you are.
ここにいたか
So that's the "eye" he was talking about.
あいつが言ってたのはそういう目のことか
To me at least, it sparkles in quite a pretty way.
俺にはきらきら光ってずいぶんと奇麗に見えるけどな
Well for now, I've got one of them.
取りあえず
まずは１本だ
Why does he sound like he's just getting started?
何だろ？
そのこれから先があるかのような物言いは
Shichika, what about Koumori?!
七花 蝙蝠は
I finished him off with an awesome move.
カッコ良くやっつけてやったよ
You missed it.
見損ねたな
ああ 残念だ
That's too bad.
Don't get me wrong, I did it for you.
勘違いしないでくれよな
あんたのためなんだからな
It's not that I want money or that I've been lured in by Shikizaki's swords.
別に俺は金に目がくらんだわけでもないし
四季崎の刀の毒が回ったわけでもないし
And I don't have a shred of obligation to help the Shogunate either.
ましてや幕府のためだなんてこれっぽっちも思っちゃいねえ
ただ　あんたのためにしたくなっただけなんだからな
I've just decided I want to help you.
I've fallen for you.
俺はあんたにほれることにしたよ
Togame-san.
とがめさん
I wanted to let you know I approve of this decision.
今回の話ですがわたしは賛成です
Is that right?
おお　そうか
I thought for sure you'd object.
てっきりそなたは反対なのだと
I suppose...
そうですね
Well to be honest, I don't really care at all about the actual basis of your journey.
いえ 正直あなたの話自体は わたしにとってはどうでもよいのです
どんな理由であれ
If that child has found a reason to leave this island, I approve of it.
あの子が外の世界に出ることにはわたしが賛成なのです
He's been on this island for 20 years, training and studying hard,
この島に渡ってから２０年
あの子が積んできた修行が
研さんしてきた技術がの実りも結ばないなんて
and it'd simply be too much of a waste if he didn't accomplish anything.
そんなの切な過ぎますから
言っておくが　七実
Just so you know, it's not going to be a simple journey.
そんな簡単な道程にはならぬぞ
There's the Maniwa corps and Sabi Hakuhei of course, and on top of that, any other monsters that may lie where we're headed.
真庭忍軍や錆白兵はもちろん
まだ　所在の知れぬ刀を所有しているのは
どんな化け物か鬼か 蛇か
Demons and serpents...
I'm bringing along your brother to fight those kinds of battles.
わたしはそういう戦いへ弟君を連れ出そうというのだ
You're quite kind, aren't you?
ずいぶんとお優しいのですね
You truly care about him, don't you.
七花のことを本当に心配してくれている
そんな　あなたになら安心して　弟を任せられます
I have no worries entrusting him to your care.
I'm...
わたしは
I'm not such a kind woman.
わたしはそのように優しい女ではない
鑢七花 お前に指示を出しておくことが４つある
Yasuri Shichika, I have four directives for you.
Four?
４つか 聞こう
Let's hear them.
First I'll repeat what I said earlier - don't break the swords.
まずさっき言ったことだ
刀は折るな
Understood.
了解 俺は刀を守ろう
I will protect the swords.
The second?
２つ目は
Protect me.
わたしを守れ
Even though our objective is the collection of Shikizaki's swords, if I die it'll all be in vain.
四季崎の刀集めが目的といっても
わたしが死んでは何にもならん
Understood.
了解 俺はあんたを守ろう
I will protect you.
３つ目は
The third?
そなた自身を守れ
Protect yourself.
This is not me being considerate of you or anything.
これはそなたをおもんばかって言っているわけではないぞ
Until we collect all 12 of Shikizaki's swords, dying is unacceptable.
四季崎の刀を１２本集めるまで
死ぬことを許さぬ
Understood.
了解 俺は俺自身を守ろう
I will protect myself.
The fourth?
４つ目は？
Protect yourself.
そなた自身を守れ
This is me being considerate of you.
これはまあ そなたをおもんばかって言っているわけだ
Don't die.
死ぬな
The road ahead will be harsh, but you mustn't die.
厳しい旅程にはなるが決して死ぬな
You can do that right?
できるな
I won't let you say you can't.
できんとは言わさんぞ 早く了解と言え
Hurry up and say you get it!
I completely understand.
極めて了解
So what do we do now?
それでどうする
No need to rush ahead.
まあ　焦るな 街に着いたら服を買ってやる
When we get to the city, I'll buy you some clothes.
Got it.
分かった
I love you.
愛してるぜ
Yep.
うむ わたしのことを好きなだけ愛せ
Love me as much as you want.
A man unknown to anyone, a woman who closed her heart.
人を知らぬ男と心をなくした女
And so those two began their journey.
こうして　２人は旅に出たのです
With no destination nor destiny, a journey to collect swords.
行き先も　行く末も知れぬ刀集めの旅に
Demons and serpents await them.
待ち受けるのは鬼か 蛇か
The story of Katanagatari on this month and this evening...
『刀語』今月こよいのお楽しみは ここまでにございます
ends here.
Though...
だけど
That child is so weak... will they be okay?
あの子あんなに弱いのに大丈夫かしら
漂う波に寄り添う華は
tadayou namini yorisou hana wa
The flowers caressed by the drifting waves
あまりにも脆く散り急く
amari ni mo moroku chirisaku
are so fragile and small
泡沫の繚乱物語
utakata no ryouran monogatari
An ephemeral abundant fairy tale
黄昏の宵月に　紅染めの月華が咲き
tasogare no yoitsuki ni benisome no geka ga saki
At dusk, the early moon, red dyed moonlight blooming
命の灯籠ともし
inochi no tomo no tamashii
Life along with soul
鋼の身体に誓いを羽織る
hagane no karada ni
On a steel body
chikai wo haotte
put on a vow
紅差す花を　守り賜う
me ni sasu hana wo
The flower that pierces the eye
mamorita mou karete nao
Protected, withered, and still...
枯れて尚
硝子の瓶に囚われ咲いた
garasu no bin ni toraware saita
Blooming while imprisoned in a glass bottle
一輪の凄惨な過去を露に溶かして
ichirin no seisanna kako wo tsuyuni tokashite
A single flower, melting a ghostly past into the dew
禊ぎの蜜に誘われし蝶の
misogi no mizu ni sasowareshi chou no
The butterflies drawn to the the water of purification
描く儚き残酷な
egaku hakanaki zankoku no
describe a fleeting, cruel
白昼の梦見物語
hakuchuu no yumemi monogatari
daydream fairy tale
尾張幕府家鳴将軍直轄
This is the army general director in support of critical tasks,
預かり奉所戦所総監督奇策士とがめだ
under direct control of Yanari Shogun of the Owari Shogunate,
Togame the strategian here.
何もかも　私の奇策通り
Everything is going according to plan.
You doubt me?
疑っているな
I also calculated you'd think that.
そなたがそう思うことも想定内
さて
Now then,
it's time for my peerless, uplifting, solemn story of justice to begin, but...
いよいよ私の痛快無比気分爽快方正謹厳な物語の始まりのわけだが
はてさて虚刀流のあの男　鑢七花
About that Kyotouryuu man,
Yasuri Shichika...
How far will he serve as my blade?
どこまで私の刀となってくれるかな
Zantou
Namakura
Next episode: Katanagatari - Zantou Namakura
次回刀語　斬刀　鈍
Cheerio!